# Mengzhe Chen (Joanne)

Mobile: (+1) 6692463650 Email:chenmz319@gmail.com https://chenmengzhe.github.io/

Sunnyvale, CA, 94087

#### **Summary**

With 5 years of research and project experience in Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR), proficient in acoustic and language modeling techniques

Objective: Full-time Research and Engineering Positions in Speech Recognition, Machine Learning and Related Fields since anytime

#### **Education**

#### 09/2011 - 07/2016 M.E. and Ph.D. Signal and Information Processing - Speech Recognition

Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS), the Institute of Acoustics

Thesis: Mandarin-English Code-mixing Speech Recognition based on Deep Neural Network

Advisor: Yonghong Yan

Recommended for admission to CAS. Received "Outstanding Student" Title

#### 09/2007 – 06/2011 **B.S. Information Engineering**

China University of Mining & Technology

GPA: 91/100 (Rank: 1/137)

Received National Scholarship, "Top Student" Award, "Outstanding Graduate" Title

### **Selected Research Experience**

#### 10/2014 – 01/2016 Mandarin-English Code-Mixing Speech Recognition System

- · Developed Mandarin-English recognition system based on deep neural network
- Optimized the method of building decision trees for alleviating data imbalance
- Optimized objective function for deep neural network training
- Proposed a method of expanding data with word vectors
- Recognition performances on code-mixing test sets improved 12%-15% relatively

#### 03/2014 – 07/2014 Knowledge Integration for Acoustic Modeling

- Introduced auxiliary knowledge into acoustic models with shared-hidden-layer networks
- Proposed n-of-V targets generated by forward-backward algorithm and correlation coefficients
- Recognition performances improved 3%-5% relatively

#### 08/2013 – 01/2014 Language Modeling for Mobile Phone Assistant System

- Constructed a speech recognition system for mobile phone assistant
- Optimized the lexicon according to non-native pronunciation habits
- Optimized class-based language model and realized it on two-level dynamic decoder
- Successfully shipped to production

## 12/2012 – 06/2013 Domain Adaptation for Language Model with Web Data for Voice Retrieval

- · Developed language model domain adaptation system for real-world voice retrieval
- Implemented web-data crawler with data preprocessing pipeline
- Proposed block-based adaptation method for building domain models
- Proposed a method of extracting hot search terms to update the lexicon
- System was applied on various domains with relative improvements of 6% -18%

## **Selected Publications**

- Chen, M., Pan, J., & Yan, Y. "Multi-Task Learning in Deep Neural Networks for Mandarin-English Code-Mixing Speech Recognition". IEICE TRANSACTIONS on Information and Systems, 2016, 99(10): 2554-2557.
- Chen, M., Zhang, Q., Wang, Z., Pan, J., & Yan, Y. "Domain Adaptation for Language Model with Web Data for Voice Retrieval". Journal of Information & Computational Science, 2015, 12(18):6883-6892.
- Chen, M., Zhang, Q., Pan, J., & Yan, Y. "Boosted Hybrid DNN/HMM System Based on Correlation-Generated Targets". In Intelligent Information Hiding and Multimedia Signal Processing, Tenth International Conference on IEEE. 2014: 590-593.

## **Technical Strengths**

Programming Languages: C/C++, perl, shell, matlab

Languages: Chinese, English